<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ead xmlns="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="urn:isbn:1-931666-22-9 https://www.loc.gov/ead/ead.xsd"><eadheader countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511"><eadid>nynyva_0003</eadid><filedesc><titlestmt><titleproper>Timothy Greathouse (1950-1998) Collection<num>   </num></titleproper></titlestmt><publicationstmt><publisher>Visual AIDS Archive</publisher><address><addressline>526 W 26th St, #309</addressline><addressline>New York. NY 10001</addressline><addressline>visualaids.org/archive</addressline><addressline>archive@visualaids.org</addressline></address></publicationstmt></filedesc><profiledesc><creation>This finding aid was produced using ArchivesSpace on <date>2025-09-30 11:37:52 -0700</date>.</creation><langusage>Description is written in: <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English, Latin script</language>.</langusage></profiledesc></eadheader><archdesc level="file">
  <did>
    <repository>
      <corpname>Visual AIDS Archive</corpname>
    </repository>
    <unittitle>Timothy Greathouse (1950-1998) Collection</unittitle>
    <unitid>   </unitid>
    <unitid type="aspace_uri">/repositories/3/resources/253</unitid>
    <physdesc altrender="whole">
      <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">2 Linear Feet</extent>
    </physdesc>
    <unitdate datechar="creation" normal="1974/2020" type="bulk">1974-2020</unitdate>
    <langmaterial>
      <language langcode="eng" scriptcode="Latn">English</language>
    </langmaterial>
  </did>
  <bioghist audience="internal" id="aspace_f64e5f1fed83ea8fcb04efd298c0b20e">
    <head>Biographical / Historical</head>
<p>Timothy Greathouse was born in 1950. He studied art at West Liberty State College in West Virginia, and later maintained a studio at the Boston Center for the Arts. He moved to New York City in 1978, following his friend and fellow artist, Darrell Nettles. He was a leading figure in the East Village art scene in the 1980's. </p><p>Inspired by close friend, Gracie Mansion, he opened multiple galleries beginning with Oggi Domani, a storefront on East 11th Street in 1984 which began as a photo gallery that later opened up to include sculpture, drawings, and later, paintings. In 1986, he moved to a larger space and renamed the gallery Greathouse, showing paintings, sculptures, and conceptual art as well as photography. He gave early shows to artist such as Kathe Burkhart, Anne Messner, Andrew Masullo, Zoe Leonard, Peter Hujar, Jimmy de Sana, and Hope Sandrow. </p><p>He closed his gallery in 1988 and worked as an art consultant and graphic designer. He passed away on October 18, 1998.</p>  </bioghist>
  <scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_fef489062550ac416d22956ae8221545">
    <head>Scope and Contents</head>
<p>Materials in the Timothy Greathouse Collection include 35mm negatives, 120mm negatives, contact sheets, photographic prints, a periodical, description of previous processing efforts, and ephemera.</p><p>The materials include portraits and photography of the work of many artists who were active in the New York Downtown art scene. There are photographs of New York City architecture and scenery, images from Fire Island, art exhibitions, New York nightlife, and some artwork documentation.</p><p>Notable subjects in the collection's photographs include: David Wojnarowicz, Sur Rodney (Sur), Kathe Burkhart, L Loffredo, Jimmy de Sana, Peter Hujar, Greer Lankton, Dean Savard, Andreas Senser, Nicholas Moufarrege, Richard Hoffman, Darrell Nettles, Gracie Mansion, Buster Cleveland, Stephen Lack, Richard Hambleton, and Rhonda Zwillinger. Notable locations include The Dakota, Pier 47, and Herman Cohen's room.</p>  </scopecontent>
  <custodhist audience="internal" id="aspace_5b0413ed8bfd0ae0c93bc88c23f84449">
    <head>Custodial History</head>
<p>These materials were originally owned by Timothy Greathouse and were given to longtime friend Darrell Nettles after Timothy's passing. Darrell Nettles donated the materials to Visual AIDS with the permission of Timothy's executor, Jay Katz, in 2025.</p>  </custodhist>
  <arrangement audience="internal" id="aspace_87d03eef488ffabb9bbffa8aa51541de">
    <head>Arrangement</head>
<p>The collection was rehoused upon arrival at Visual AIDS but kept in original order. This original arrangement was overseen by Sur Rodney (Sur) and rehoused by Jacs Rodriguez. Any original notations were maintained and added to rehoused materials.</p>  </arrangement>
  <relatedmaterial audience="internal" id="aspace_8566972b43a369a8020ef5dc5022b259">
    <head>Related Materials</head>
<p>There are further materials related to Timothy Greathouse in the Visual AIDS Artist Files collection.</p><p>Many of the photographs included in this collection are also reproduced in an exhibition catalog available in the Visual AIDS library - "Tim Greathouse" (N 4784 .G7438 2020).</p>  </relatedmaterial>
  <processinfo audience="internal" id="aspace_643ebfb3106fd001bfe9f035f071ebab">
    <head>Processing Information</head>
<p>This collection was processed and arranged by Jacs Rodriguez in 2025.</p>  </processinfo>
  <dsc><c audience="internal" id="aspace_d1d9fd76666d6e40b48098213e4b502e" level="otherlevel" otherlevel="Box"><did><unittitle>Photo Binder 1</unittitle><unitid type="aspace_uri">/repositories/3/archival_objects/30996</unitid><unitdate datechar="creation" normal="1974/1990" type="inclusive">1974-1990</unitdate></did><scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_444ac33d888199717425d0491867468f"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This binder contains 120mm photographic negatives, 35mm photographic negatives, and photographic prints. These materials are dated 1974 - 1990.</p><p>The photos in this container include portraits, self-portraits, landscape photography, photography of New York generally, nightlife photography, personal photography, and artwork documentation.</p></scopecontent></c><c audience="internal" id="aspace_44d7bd5122633ec5872e3d614d19dc9f" level="otherlevel" otherlevel="Box"><did><unittitle>Photo Binder 2</unittitle><unitid type="aspace_uri">/repositories/3/archival_objects/30997</unitid><unitdate datechar="creation" normal="1978/1984" type="inclusive">1978-1984</unitdate></did><scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_6aae0f7175c747e31553e7d4930201d6"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This binder contains 35mm photographic negatives and contact sheets. The materials are dated 1978 - 1984.</p><p>The photos in this container include New York photography, portraits, male nudes, event and nightlife photography, and artwork documentation.</p></scopecontent></c><c audience="internal" id="aspace_31a11554b8b2bc4b46423eddb69d042c" level="otherlevel" otherlevel="Box"><did><unittitle>Archival Box</unittitle><unitid type="aspace_uri">/repositories/3/archival_objects/30998</unitid><unitdate datechar="creation" normal="1979/2020" type="inclusive">1979-2020</unitdate></did><scopecontent audience="internal" id="aspace_cf37c256116a151854f36e57a72e79b3"><head>Scope and Contents</head><p>This box contains photographic prints, ephemera, a periodical, photographic negatives, and a description of the original order of organization for the collection. These materials are dated 1979-2020.</p><p>The photos in this container include portraits and New York photography. </p></scopecontent></c></dsc>
</archdesc>
</ead>
